A Guide to the American Rhododendron Society Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10553-u
American Rhododendron Society Papers ca. 1968-1989
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10553-u
ca. 1200 items
American Rhododendron Society
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the Library on April 22, 1991, by the American Rhododendron Society through Barbara R. Hall, Executive Secretary, Gloucester, Virginia.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of the American Rhododendron Society, chiefly during the presidency of George W. Ring III of Fairfax, Virginia, ca. 1200 items (4 Hollinger boxes, ca. one linear foot), ca. 1968-1989, including Board of Director minutes, correspondence, financial records, topical files, and committee correspondence files.
Committee correspondence files include: the Budget and Finance Committee, with financial statements and reports (see also Financial Reports); the Honors Committee re the awarding of gold and silver medals as recognition for contributions to rhododendrons and the American Rhododendron Society; the Nominating Committee concerning nominations for national officers; the first three years of the Publicity Committee created in October of 1981 and chaired by Colonel Wallace Marley, chiefly regarding his attempts to persuade the United States Postal Service to choose native American azaleas and rhododendrons for a stamp; the Membership Committee; the Research Committtee founded in 1970 which sponsored the formation of the A.R.S. Research Foundation in 1976 and under its auspices continues to provide funds for various research projects, with a Q & A sheet describing the A.R.S. research program (1983 Feb); the Ratings Committee, and its efforts to include a performance rating in addition to the rating of both the plant and flower quality in order to receive a national award; the Shows and Judging Committee with "Judging Rules and the Development of Uniform Judging Practices" (n.d.) and a Report on Shows and Judging (1979-1980, 1982); and the Publications Committee concerning the book purchasing service. There are several folders of correspondence with or about the Rhododendron Species Foundation.
The Board of Directors correspondence is chiefly about the elections of the District Directors, with copies of letters from A.R.S. members to various Congressmen urging a commemorative stamp featuring native American azaleas and rhododendrons. The general correspondence folder discusses the problems of several individuals within the organization, general inquiries, and difficulties of members with book orders from Theophrastus, dues, and other matters.
The correspondence file with Marion and Vernon May of the Publicity Committee discusses the new A.R.S. Chapter Notebooks (1982 Jul 7 & Aug 4, n.d.); ideas for the Publicity part of the Chapter Notebook from a local news editor (1982 Jan 30); letters while on a Rhododendron Tour to Australia, New Zealand, and Tasmania, with newsclippings about the tour (1982, 1982 Aug 22, Oct 20, and Nov 10); news of rhododendron growing and A.R.S. business (1982 Aug 4); and the Seed Exchange and its funds (1982 Dec 16).
There are several folders about various awards available in the American Rhododendron Society. These include the Pioneer Achievement Award with Joseph B. Gable as its first receipient. The Awards folder discusses the value and difficulties of the plant award program and the response of chapters to the proposition for dropping it. Related material is located in the Ratings Committee and the Shows and Judging Committee files.
Other items of interest include chapter activities, the canvass of chapters, the computarization of rhododendron hybrids, "Landscaping with Rhododendrons" and reviews of several papers about rhododendrons by George Ring.
Container List
- Annual Meetings, 1981-1982 (Box Box 1)
- Awards, 1980-1983 (Box Box 1)
- Bed and Breakfast Proposal for ARS Members (Box Box 1)
- Board of Directors Correspondence, 1981-1984 (Box Box 1)
- Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1981-3, 1986-9; (2 folders) (Box Box 1)
- Budget and Finance Committee, 1981-1984 (Box Box 1)
- Chapter Activities, 1981 (Box Box 1)
- Chapters, Canvass of; and Replies, 1979-1980 (Box Box 1)
- Chapter Presidents, 1981-1982 (Box Box 1)
- Computarization of Rhododendron Hybrids, 1979-1980 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1978-1983 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence with Marion and Vernon May, 1981-1983 (Box Box 1)
- Financial Reports, 1968-1981 (Box Box 2)
- Honors Committee, 1977-1983; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
- International Meeting, 1981-1983 (Box Box 2)
- "Landscaping with Rhododendrons" (Box Box 2)
- Member Services, 1979-1981 (Box Box 2)
- Membership Committee, 1977-1983 (Box Box 2)
- Nominating Committee, 1979-1983 (Box Box 2)
- Pioneer Award, 1979-1982; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
- Policies of Board, 1980-1981, 1988 (Box Box 3)
- Pollen Bank, 1980-1983 (Box Box 3)
- Preservation, 1980 (Box Box 3)
- Publications Committee, 1981-1983 (Box Box 3)
- Publicity Committee, 1981-1983; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
- Ratings Committee, 1978-1983 (Box Box 3)
- Registrar, 1979-1983 (Box Box 3)
- Research Committee, 1981-1983; (3 folders) (Box Box 3)
- Reviews of Papers re Rhododendrons by George Ring, 1980-1983 (Box Box 3)
- Rhododendron Species Foundation, 1973-1984, n.d.; (5 folders) (Box Box 4)
- Seed Exchange, 1980-1983 (Box Box 4)
- Shows & Judging Committee, 1979-1983 (Box Box 4)
- Slide Shows, 1981-1983 (Box Box 4)
- Tax Exempt Status, 1982 (Box Box 4)
- United States Department of Agriculture Bulletin and Erik Neumann, 1976-1979 (Box Box 4)
- Western Regional Rhododendron Conference, 1981 (Box Box 4)
- Financial Records kept on Columnar Pad, 1981-1982; (2 items) (Box Oversize Folder)